Sofia Dutta

Software Engineer

in https://linkedin.com/in/sofiadutta https://sofiadutta.github.io

Software Engineer with a decade of experience working with large quantities of data. Worked on every aspect of the software development life cycle, from design & development of core functionality to production deployments in cloud environments. Seeking software engineering opportunities in the US.

SKILLS

Programming – Python, Java, SQL, PL/SQL

Data Science – Apache PySpark, Looker, LookML, PyTorch, Sci-kit Learn, Tensorflow, Hadoop Data/Software Engineering – Apache Airflow, Databricks, Jupyter Notebook, Google Colab, Git Cloud – Google Cloud Platform, Google Compute Engine, Google Cloud Storage, Google Cloud SQL, AWS S3 Back-end – Google BigQuery Table, Oracle Databases, PostgreSQL, MySQL, MongoDB, JSON Domain knowledge – Big Data Analytics, Deep Learning, Machine Learning

WORK EXPERIENCE

Technical Leader @ NewWave Telecom & Technologies, Inc., Windsor Mill, MD, USA

Jan 2021 – Present

- Designed the system architecture, database schema, and data workflow for the Imersis data quality analytics
- Built the project's cloud infrastructure setup and processed hundreds of millions of healthcare records using Apache PySpark to compute data quality metrics.
- Created Looker dashboard visualizations with drill-down options that "explains" why the data quality came out to a certain value.
- Due to the lack of large quantities of data, re-designed the machine learning goal of the project into a data quality "Explainable AI" system.
- Built a data quality system that allows clients to understand how to improve their data quality over time.
- Using a four-fold workflow automation strategy saved tens of thousands of dollars in cloud costs for the project.

Data Science Intern @ NewWave Telecom & Technologies, Inc., Windsor Mill, MD, USA

May 2020 - Dec 2020

- Helped speed up the project's data processing pipeline 10-fold by moving to Google Cloud Platform (GCP).
- Managed DevOps on GCP and connected the cloud infrastructure to back-end Big Data tables for delivering results to dashboards.

Software Engineer @ Tata Consultancy Services, Kolkata, India

Nov 2006 – Feb 2018

- Led the design, development, and delivery of API interfaces using PL/SQL stored procedures for several projects of TCS.
- Carried out change-based regression impact analysis, created software functional specifications, and prepared test plans for several projects of TCS.
- Performed system integration, user acceptance, and performance testing and ensured client systems had very high uptime even when carrying out data migration activities.
- Saved millions of dollars in potential revenue lost to the client and was awarded for the said effort by clients.

EDUCATION

Udacity Nanodegree: Deep Learning

Masters in Data Science from the University of Maryland, Baltimore County, Baltimore, MD

Oct 2021

Jan 2019 – Dec 2020 Jun 2006 - Nov 2010

Bachelor's in Computer Science from West Bengal University of Technology, Kolkata, India